When you first look at it, the stress shifts may seem arbitrary, but let's
examine the logic behind these five examples and use it to go on to other,
similar cases. 1. An American guy. The operative word is American. Guy could even
be left out without changing the meaning of the phrase. Compare I saw two American
guys yesterday with I saw two Americans yesterday. Words like guy, man, kid, lady,
people are de facto pronouns in an anthropocentric language. A strong noun,
on the other hand, would be stressed. They flew an American flag. This is why you
have the pattern change, Jim killed a man, he killed a snake. 2. An American
restaurant Don't be sidetracked by an ordinary descriptive phrase that happens
to have a nationality in it. restaurant. We went to a good restaurant yesterday. Or
we went to an American restaurant yesterday. You would use the same pattern
where the nationality is more or less incidental in, I had French toast for
breakfast. French fry, on the other hand, has become a set phrase. 3. American food.
Food is a weak word. I never ate American food when I lived in Japan.
4. An English teacher. This is a description so the stress is on teacher. 5. An English
teacher. This is a set phrase. The stress is on the subject being taught, not on the
nationality of the teacher. A French teacher, a Spanish teacher, a history
teacher.